Guide to the Religious organizations of Brooklyn collection ARC.242
Brooklyn Historical Society
Religious organizations of Brooklyn collection
1828-1986
1841-1931
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.242
1.75 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes and one oversize folder.
The religious organizations of Brooklyn collection contains records and publications of several church-affiliated and interdenominational charities, shelters, schools, and missions estalished in Brooklyn in the 19th and 20th centuries.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of this collection were the gifts of Mrs. Henry E. Drake, 1986, and St. Phebe's Mission, 1915. Sources and dates of acquisition for the majority of the collection are unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by organization name.
Historical note
The widespread emergence of religious organizations devoted to philanthropy in New York City began with the revival of Protestantism in the early 19th century. The reemergence of Protestantism encouraged its followers to provide spiritual and material aid to those in need, and evangelicals responded by establishing a number of benevolent organizations, such as the American Tract Society and the American Bible Society, which were dedicated to the distribution of the scriptures, and the American Sunday School Union, which labored for the establishment of Sunday schools in rural areas. Other Protestant groups founded homes to shelter and care for orphans, widows, unwed mothers, the disabled, and the unemployed. Groups of other religious denominations, including Catholics and Jews, soon followed accordingly and established their own charities, shelters, societies, schools, and missions.
Despite their denominational affiliations, several religious organizations also supported interdenominational work so as to provide as wide-reaching a benefit as possible. While much of the highly-publicized philanthropy in 19th-century New York was the work of wealthy private citizens, such as Peter Cooper, John Jacob Astor, and Charles Pratt, religious organizations were instrumental to the burgeoning of philanthropy in the city, as their members, many of whom were women, conducted their roles as teachers, nurses, social workers, and missionaries for very low wages.
Sources:
Hammock, David C. "Philanthropy," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 896-898.
Scope and Contents
The religious organizations of Brooklyn collection contains records and publications of various religious philanthropic organizations estalished in Brooklyn in the 19th and 20th centuries. Materials in the collection span the period 1828 to 1986, with the bulk dating between 1841 and 1931.
The majority of the material consists of annual reports and manuals containing comprehensive information on several organizations' yearly activities and accomplishments. Most of these are contained as individual yearly publications, though some are compiled in bound volumes. The reports and manuals typically include historical information on an organization; lists of officers, directors, managers, and committees; reports from various officers within an organization; financial statements; minutes and proceedings from annual meetings; lists of donors and contributors; and lists of member churches, individual members, and subscribers.
The remainder of the collection consists of various publications and ephemera, including individually published articles of incorporation, constitutions, and bylaws; case study reports; newsletters; programs for fundraising events; informational pamphlets and brochures; and catalogs.
Constitutions; Circulars (fliers); Articles of incorporation; Bylaws (administrative records); Catalogs; Subscription lists; Brochures; Programs (documents); Minutes; Financial statements; Membership lists; Proceedings; Reports; Pamphlets; Volumes (documents by form); Annual reports; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Missionaries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Printed ephemera; Women in church work -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Presbyterian Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Missions; Long Island (N.Y.); Methodists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Lutheran Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Lutheran Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Old age homes -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Lutherans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Baptists -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Baptists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Baptists -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Missions; Social settlements -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Catholics -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religious institutions -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Charitable giving; Catholic Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Sunday schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church work with the poor -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Congregationalists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church societies -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church charities -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church charities -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- History; Jews -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jews -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Congregational churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Presbyterian Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Protestants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Presbyterian Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Presbyterians -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Methodist Episcopal Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church work with immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bible -- Publication and distribution -- Societies, etc.; Methodist Episcopal Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Charities; Youth in church work -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Youth -- Societies and clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hebrew Educational Society of Brooklyn; International Catholic Truth Society; Warren Street Mission (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Woman's American Baptist Home Mission Society. Long Island Division; Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society; Sixth Avenue Baptist Sunday School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Boys' Mission Band; Congregational Church Extension Society of New York City and Brooklyn; Brooklyn Association in Aid of the Grande-Ligne Mission (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Helping Hand of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Union for Christian Work (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn City Bible Society; Brooklyn Hebrew Orphan Asylum; Baptist Children's Home of Long Island (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Long Island Baptist Association. Children's Home. Women's Board; Brooklyn City Tract Society; Daughters of Israel Benefit Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Wartburg Lutheran Home for Aged and Infirm (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.. Synod of Long Island. Woman's Home and Foreign Missionary Society; Christian Union for Work Among the Chinese (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Woman's Baptist Missionary Society. Long Island Division; Society of St. Vincent de Paul. Diocesan Central Council of Brooklyn; St. Phebe's Mission and Convalescent Home (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Evangelical Home Society of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Evangelical Home for the Aged; Brooklyn Tabernacle (New York, N.Y.); Women's Baptist Home Mission Society. Long Island Division; St. Phebe's Mission; Church Mission of Help (Episcopal Church). Diocese of Long Island; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.. Presbytery of Brooklyn-Nassau; Mercy Home for Children (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Missionary Training Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York Port Society; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.. Presbytery of Brooklyn. Woman's Home and Foreign Missionary Society; Prospect Heights Presbyterian Church (New York, N.Y.). Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor; Auxiliary Foreign Mission Society of New-York and Brooklyn; Woman's Baptist Foreign Missionary Society. Long Island Division; Woman's National Sabbath Alliance. Brooklyn Auxiliary; Long Island Baptist Association. Children's Home; American McAll Association. Brooklyn Auxiliary; American Sunday-School Union. Foreign Sunday-School Association; Brooklyn Baptist Orphanage; Foreign Sunday School Association
- Auxiliary Foreign Mission Society of New York and Brooklyn, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  First annual report.
- Baith Israel Congregation, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Constitution and by-laws.
- Baptist Children's Home of Long Island, 1927-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  Woman's board by-laws, undated; manuals, 1927-1928 and 1946-1947; fiftieth aniversary program, 1951; report, 1948-1949; benefit concert programs, 1947-1961.
- Bible and Tract Society, Brooklyn Tabernacle, 1909-1912 (Box OS-20)
  People's Pulpit newsletter Vols. 1-4.
- Brooklyn Association in Aid of the Grand-Ligne Mission, 1859-1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Annual reports.
- Brooklyn Auxiliary to the McCall Mission in France, 1882, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Brooklyn Baptist Orphanage, 1910-1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Manuals.
  Related Materials
  Also represented under its subsequent name, Baptist Children's Home of Long Island.
- Brooklyn City Bible Society, 1841-1892 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society, 1854-1855, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Annual reports and fundraising card.
  Historical note
  Also known as the Brooklyn City Tract Society.
- Brooklyn Hebrew Orphan Asylum, 1905, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Brooklyn Union for Christian Work, 1867-1900 (Box 2, Volume 1-2)
- Christian Union for Work Among the Chinese, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Fourth anniversary pamphlet.
- Church Mission of Help, 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Congregational Church Extension in New York City and Brooklyn, 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Custodial History
  Inscribed "Geo. C. Brainerd 56 Wall St. N.Y.C."
  Annual report.
- Evangelical Home for the Aged, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Foreign Sunday School Association, 1872-1904 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Hebrew Educational Society, 1959, 1961, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  Annual reports and June 1961 issue of H.E.S. Bulletin.
- Helping Hand of Brooklyn, 1871, 1877, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Articles of incorporation and by-laws; annual report, 1877; Night Mission annual report, 1891.
- International Catholic Truth Society, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Catalogue No. 1: Catholic Fiction.
- Mercy Home for Children, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Mercy Matters newsletter.
- Missionary Training Institute, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- New York Port Society, 1893-1894 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Biographical / Historical
  "Society for Promoting the Gospel Among Seamen in the Port of New York" at the Mariner's Church, 46 Catharine Street; Brooklyn branch, 31 Atlantic Avenue.
- Presbytery of Brooklyn-Nassau, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Expansion fund booklet.
- Saint Phebe's Mission, 1881-1927 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  Annual reports; Opening program; informational flyers.
  Also known as St. Phebe's Mission and Convalescent Home.
- Sixth Avenue Baptist Sunday School, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  The Kanzensha newsletter, Vol. 1 No. 12.
- Society of St. Vincent De Paul, 1905-1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Annual reports; Golden Jubilee program, 1905.
- Warren Street Mission, 1853-1854 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Articles of association and manual.
- Wartburg Lutheran Home, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  75th anniversary program.
- Woman's Baptist Missionary Society, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Woman's Home and Foreign Missionary Society [Presbyterian], 1874, circa 1882 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Manual (1874) and annual report.
- Woman's National Sabbath Alliance, 1913-1915 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Pamphlet, manuals, booklist.
- Women's Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1885, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Annual report and magazine article from The Examiner, a Baptist newspaper.
- Women's Baptist Home Mission Society, 1899-1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Constitution, financial notes and ephemera. Associated with Prospect Heights Presbyterian Church.